Inventory of the Spas T. Raikin Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Spas T. Raikin papers
1922-2011
80148
Raikin, Spas T., 1922-
55 manuscript boxes (22 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, writings, bulletins, serial issues, printed matter, and photographs, relating to Bulgarian history, the Bulgarian Orthodox Eastern Church, Bulgarian émigré affairs, and activities of anti-communist organizations, including the Anti-Bolshevik Bloc of Nations and the Bulgarian National Front.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1980, with a voluminous increment received in 2012.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
A Bulgarian-American historian, Raikin served as secretary of the Central Executive Board, Bulgarian National Council, from 1960 to 1963.
Born to a poor peasant family, Raikin herded cows and sheep until he was admitted to the Plovdiv Theological Seminary. He graduated with honors and went on to study in the School of Theology in Sofia University and teach in the Sofia Theological Seminary. Once the Bulgarian Communists had solidified their power, they intensified their religious persecution, drafting Raikin into the army, where he served his time in a military labor camp. In 1951, he and several of his friends escaped from the camp and formed a partisan group in the Rhodope Mountains in southern Bulgaria. Evading the Communists, they managed to cross into Greece, where he received a scholarship from the World Council of Churches to study theology at the University of Athens. He went on to study at the universities in Geneva, Basel, and King's College in London, finally taking a graduate degree in political science at Columbia University in New York. In New York, Raikin became a social worker who helped resettle Bulgarian refugees in the United States under a State Department Program, as well as a staff member in the Travelers Aid Society. It was in that capacity that he was directed to meet Lee Harvey Oswald upon his return from Russia. Raikin found a hotel room for Oswald, his wife, and baby, and handed him a check that paid for their move to Fort Worth, Texas. His account of this event is in the Warren Commission Report and is discussed in dozens of works on the Kennedy assassination.
Raikin's academic career was mostly with East Stroudsburg University in Pennsylvania, where he taught from 1966 until his retirement in 1991. He published some twenty books on Bulgarian history, politics, and culture from the late nineteenth century into the twentieth. He was also active in Bulgarian and East European anticommunist exile organizations.
Additional biographical information may be found in box 1.
Scope and Content of Collection
Raikin's papers, contained in ninety-nine binders, document Rhis historical research and writing as well as Bulgarian émigré activities in the United States.
Spas T. Raikin notes, "The following?99 volumes of my archives are a mirror of my political activities in exile. They contain information on historical, political, social, and ecclesiastical events in the turbulent 20th century in which I personally participated, witnessed and interpreted."
"Some of this information was published in my twenty volumes in the [several] series Politicheski problemi pred bulgarskata obshtestvenost v chuzhbina (Political Problems Facing the Bulgarian Community Abroad), five volumes, Politichesko pateshestvie sreshtu vetrovete na XX vek (Political Journey Against the Winds of the XX Century), thirteen volumes, and San Stefanska Bulgaria. Poiava, sudba, triumf i tragedia na bulgarskata natsionalna ideia (Origins, Fate, Triumph and Tragedy of the Bulgarian National Idea), two volumes."
"Articles, documents, essays, papers and commentaries not included in the above publications are in these Archives. I believe that all these materials - published or not published, but saved here - will serve well future scholars in understanding and interpreting Bulgarian history of our age, specifically our exile movement." Spas T. Raikin, 29 November 2011, Stroudsburg, Pennsylvania, Box 1
Binder number 71, however, is different from the others. It contains copies of documents, notes, and clippings about his meeting with Lee Harvey Oswald in the port at Hoboken, New Jersey on June 13, 1962, when Oswald was returning from the Soviet Union.
Arranged by Raikin in numerical order by binder, with all titles retained. Although Raikin created 99 volumes, he did not include number 78 in the collection.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Bŭlgarska pravoslavna tsŭrkva.; Anti-Bolshevik Bloc of Nations.; Bulgarian National Front.; Anti-communist movements.; Bulgarians--United States.; Bulgaria--Emigration and immigration.; Bulgaria--History.
Collection Contents
- Arranged by Raikin in numerical order by binder; all titles were retained
- Writings, memoranda, and declarations relating to Bulgaria, Bulgarian émigré, and the Bulgarian National Council, received in 1980 (formerly 10.V) (File 1)
- Preface, photographs, biography notes, my creed, editorial principles, "Escape from Hell," "Epilogue - Evil's Flowers," documents, contents of archives (File 1: 1)
- Family history, personal documents, letters from and to my brothers (File 1: 2)
- Personal, letters to and from family in Bulgaria (File 2: 3)
- Documents, originals and copies, Marin, Bezmer, Trudovak, World Council of Churches, Lavrion, Switzerland, England (File 3: 4)
- Darzhavna Sigurnost, dossier "Desertiori," "Bulgarian Sum" (File 4: 5-6)
- King Simeon (File 5: 7)
- American Bulgarian League (File 5: 8)
- Arrival in America, Diary first seven weeks, politics and refugees, Church World Service, 1954-1955 (File 6: 9)
- Bulgarian National Front (BNF) first congress, political report, Kalin Koichev, Ivan Dochev, Paprikov, MPO, church politics and refugees (File 6: 10)
- Borba edited by Raikin, #1-21, 1956-1963 (File 7: 11-12)
- American Friends Anti-Bolshevik Block of Nations, Raikin, Secretary General, 1958-1960 (File 8: 13)
- Metropolitan, Andrey (File 8: 14)
- Bulgarian National Front (Box 9-10)
  - 1954-1958 (File 9: 15-16)
  - 1959 (File 10: 17)
- Bulgarian National Front and Bulgarian National Council (Box 10-14)
  - 1960 (File 10: 18)
  - 1961 (File 11: 19)
  - 1961 (File 12: 20)
  - 1962 (File 13: 21-22)
  - 1963 (File 14: 23-24)
- Independent, 1964-1970 (File 15: 25)
- Bulgarian Agrarian National Union (Box 16-18)
  - 1971-1976 (File 16: 26-27)
  - 1977-1985 (File 17: 28-29)
  - 1986-1998 (File 18: 30)
- Free Agrarian Banner (Box 18-20)
  - No. 1-20, 1978-1982 (File 18: 31)
  - No. 49-67, 1982-1990 (File 19: 32-33)
  - Bank accounts (File 20: 34)
- Published and unpublished articles (File 20: 35)
- Papers and articles, published and not published (File 21: 36-37)
- Unpublished papers and articles (File 22: 38)
- San Stefanska Bulgaria, English original text (File 22: 39)
- San Stefanska Bulgaria, English original text (File 23: 40-41)
- Scrapbook, Zhelev, Stoyanov, Project Political Program BNF, Washington declaration, Spas, Tantikov, et al. (File 24: 42)
- Bulgarian Orthodox Church under communism, Senate hearing, my report for Bolan court case (File 24: 43)
- Trudovak, Marin, long hand texts (File 25: 44)
- Schism in the Bulgarian Orthodox Church 1 (File 25: 45)
- Schism in the Bulgarian Orthodox Church 2 (not published papers) (File 26: 46)
- Schism in the Bulgarian Orthodox Church 3-4, 1992-2002 (File 26: 47-48)
- Schism in the Bulgarian Orthodox Church 5, 1992-2002 (File 27: 49)
- Court case, Varba-Nov vs. St. Andrey, Attorney Bolan 1 (File 27: 50)
- Court case, Varba-Nov vs. St. Andrey, Attorney Bolan 2 (File 28: 51)
- Raskol in New York, Schismatics vs. Metropolitan Joseph II (File 28: 52)
- Chicago, Munich, Raskol, 1992-2002 (File 29: 53)
- Correspondence (File 30: 54)
- Free Agrarian Banner edited by Raikin, 1981-1983 (File 30: 54)
- Personal correspondence, family in Bulgaria (File 31: 55)
- General correspondence, New York Times, Pocono records, Chicago churches, et al. (File 31: 56)
- Important correspondence, Patriarch Pavle of Serbia, Dr. Ivan Gadjev, Meytropolitan Kiril Yonchev, Petar Nikolov (File 32: 57)
- My dossier in "Darzhavna Sigurnost" Sofia, Bulgaria, my dossiers in CIA and FBI, State Department, Filchev, Attorney General, Sofia, Bulgaria (File 32: 58)
- Political VIP in my orbit, Borislav, Dochev, Radi, G. M., Dimitrov, Shivarov (File 33: 59)
- Omitted or repeated materials, VIP BNF, BNC, schism, refugees, seminarians, lost pages, omitted letters (File 34: 60)
- Bulgarian Orthodox Chuch under communism, my resistance, Joseph I Kalin, Koichev (File 35: 61)
- Bulgarian Orthodox Church, New York diocese, Joseph II and Raikin vs. Schismatics, Joseph II confession (File 35: 62)
- Bulgarian Orthodox Church, New York diocese, Joseph II and Raikin vs. Schismatics (File 36: 63)
- Diocese in good and bad times, documentation: Schismatics vs. Joseph in court action, analysis by Raikin (File 36: 64)
- Analysis by Raikin, papers against the Schismatics, in defense of the Bulgarian Orthodox Church, miscellaneous (File 37: 65)
- Miscellaneous: omitted items, personal principles, drafts, unpublished documents and essays, maps (File 37: 66)
- General correspondence, alphabetical (Box 38-42)
  - A-G (File 38: 67-68)
  - H-N (File 39: 69-70)
  - O-S. Includes Lee Harvey Oswald materials (File 40: 71)
  - S-T (File 41: 72)
  - U-Z (File 42: 73)
- Miscellaneous correspondence, 1992-1993 (File 42: 74)
- Miscellaneous correspondence, 1984-1985 (File 43: 75)
- Munich correspondence, RFE, Darvodelski vs. Raikin, Stephan Popov, Rodopi Odyssey, Post-communist era letters, memorandum to president Bush, failure in the Middle East, Julia Daskalova, "Nedelnik," Velko Valkanov (File 43: 76)
- The Theodores, Momar Quaddafi, Chicago cultural affairs, Simeon Ovcharov, Raikovski (File 44: 77)
- Not sent to Hoover Institution by Raikin (File 44: 78)
- Correspondence, Tsanyo P. Tsvaitkov, commentaries, post-communist Bulgaria (File 44: 79)
- Robert Chipperfield, press forums, commentaries, Bulgarian politics (File 45: 80)
- Corduffe, Emil, Australia, commentary, e-mail (File 45: 81)
- Pocono Record letters to the editor, 1970-2011 (File 46: 82)
- Important omissions, letters, commentaries, documents (File 46: 83)
- Samples, articles, Bulgarian press, 2000-2005 (File 47: 84)
- Political commentaries, internet pages (Box 47-51)
  - 2001 (File 47: 85)
  - 2002 (File 48: 86-87)
  - 2002-2003 (File 49: 88-89)
  - 2003 (File 50: 90-91)
  - 2004-2005 (File 51: 92-93)
- Defective English text of San Stefanska Bulgaria 1 (File 52: 94)
- Defective English text of San Stefanska Bulgaria 2 (File 53: 95)
- Unpublished essays, articles, conference papers, historical studies (File 53: 96)
- Introduction to philosophy notes, 1964-1965, lectures (File 54: 97)
- Personal promotion papers (File 54: 98)
- Personal correspondents: Altunkov, Miro G., Mitropolit Simeon Ing. Doichin, Penev (File 54: 98)
- Personal correspondents: Gadjec, Rev. Peniu, Tsvaitkov, Todorov, Jordan, Perle, Richard, commentaries (File 55: 99)